In the first half of this talk I'm going to try to slip two plots by you that
show some sort of problematic data quality issue. So if when I do that you
you happen to notice that, just act like you've fallen asleep and so that way if
everybody looks like they've fallen asleep I know that the talk is engaging.
So a year or so ago we were working on an agent for data analysis and it was
sort of cloud code shaped but it also had the ability to run Python code. And
we wanted to make sure that when the agent made plots it could see the plots.
So I load in the tips data set and I say please plot the total bill versus the tip.
So when people tip at a restaurant they tend to calculate it as a percentage so
we would expect that as the total bill increases the tip increases as well. So a
positive relationship. So I send this message to the agent that I'm working on.
It runs some Python code, it returns a plot, and it says there's a strong
positive association. Okay nobody's acting like they're asleep so that's
good for engagement I think. There's an issue here which is that the plot is
showing that as the total bill increases the tip seems to decrease. So I order a
$2 drink and the tip is $10 for some reason and a $50 meal and for some
reason folks are tipping $2. This is weird and this is because I added a
little trick before I asked the agent to make that plot. I wanted to make sure
it could actually see the plots so I took the value of the total bill and
subtracted that from the maximum value so that every time I plot the total bill
against any other variable inside of the data set I would see the opposite of the
relationship that I would expect to see. And I wanted to test the vision of this
agent so I assumed if the agent can actually see the plot it's going to tell
me that oh that's weird for some reason the relationship is the opposite of what
I expected. And yet for some reason it didn't do so. So we were looking at the
API documentation again and again like oh maybe this JSON field needs to be
pushed inside of an element or something like that or I've used the wrong base 64
encoding and if I switch to a different library it'll work. So we try all these
things and it's not working and out of desperation we try one more approach. We
say run this code, only this code, nothing but this code, tell me how many points
there are and what color they are. This is some seaborn code. I'm taking a number
between 2 and 10. I'm plotting that many points on a Cartesian plane and I'm
assigning those points a random color. So I'm sampling an RG and a B and every
time the agent runs that code because we don't know the state of the random
number generator the number of points in the color will be different. And so in
order to be able to tell me how many points there are and what color they are
the agent has to actually be able to see the plot. So I say run this code, only
this code, nothing but this code. The agent runs the code. It sees there are
three cyan points and it says so. I thought it wasn't working. We had tried
all this stuff of hitting the APIs in different ways thinking that we were
making some mistake but it turns out that the agents actually for some
reason can see the plots just fine but in this case where their priors are
being controverted they refuse to say so. So my colleague Sarah and I put this
blog post together called when plotting LLM see what they expect to see and the
evidence we use in that blog post is an LLM evaluation called BluffBench.
BluffBench puts these models in a bunch of situations like this where axis
labels might indicate to the agent that they should expect to see some
relationship like as the total bill increases the tip should increase but
then the evidence shown in the plot is actually the opposite of that. At the
time the frontier models of the time did terribly on this so GPT-5, GeminiPro
2.5 and CloudSonic 4.5 were the leading models from the major labs. We tried so
much stuff short of saying by the way this plot is going to contradict your
priors tell me what's actually in it to try to drive these scores up and we
really struggled to do so. Hilariously we enabled thinking and then looked at the
thinking traces afterward and the model would say huh that doesn't look like I
expected it to. It would close the thinking tag and then say looks like I
expected. So of course the best way to drive the score up on an LLM evaluation
is to wait six months and the plot looks a little bit like this now. So with
with thinking disabled the scores sort of bunch around 25% and over time they
tend to get a little bit better. The leading models of the day on on this
evaluation which are CloudFable 5 and Gemini 3 flash tend to be in the
ballpark of like 70% on this. Notably this is subhuman. I would guess that
anybody in the audience here would score around 100% on these. These are not
subtle contradictions of your priors. This is literally like we're flipping
the axis on each plot. And so from this we learn that models largely fail to
override their own priors about data when they're presented with evidence
that contradicts. There are all sorts of issues with BluffBench. The the
evaluation only presents the sorts of information and tools that the model
needs to sort of activate the prior and then see whether the agent will
contradict it or not. And so since then we've wondered what if we put these
models in a data analysis situation that looks a lot more like real world data
analysis. So we give it a bunch of stuff that doesn't matter. Like you put it in
a harness that looks like cloud code or something like that and you tell it to
load in some data and you have a bunch of back and forth until eventually you
ask it to make some plot and that plot has some sort of very subtle artifact
inside of the visualization that could feasibly result from a real data
generating process. So for example let's assume that I receive some patient data
and I'm just making some exploratory plots to understand what's going on. I
say could you plot BMI versus cholesterol. The agent runs some code and
it generates a plot that shows that the BMI tends to well as the BMI increases
the cholesterol tends to increase. Okay nobody's sleeping so it seems like the
audience is engaged. There's something a little weird going on here. I'll zoom in
on this a little bit. As the BMI increases the cholesterol tends to
increase except that in the middle sort of right along where you would expect
the fitted line to land there are a bunch of points. And so if we take a step
back and we're like that's weird what's going on. Turns out if you filter down to
one of the clinics that contributed data they didn't include cholesterol and
the data model imputed the cholesterol value for those points. So if I were to
then go and do data analysis on this data set without realizing this I would
make a bunch of errors. And so I either need to filter those out or change them
to missing values or use measures that meaningfully incorporate the fact that
some of these points are synthetic. It turns out that even today's frontier
models do terribly on this sort of thing. So we designed a follow up LLM
evaluation called Bluff Bench 2 that is very similar to Bluff Bench except that
it feels a lot more like real world data analysis. And even those same leaders
Cloud Fable 5 and Gemini 3 Flash are sort of in the mid teens in terms of the
percent of cases where they actually notice that something is awry in the moment
that they need to. So from the second evaluation we learned something a little
bit more general which is that models fail to notice subtle data quality issues
that most data scientists would not miss. One might think at this point should we
burn it all down. Should we be using LLMs for data analysis at all. I'll hand it
off to my colleague Sarah to answer that question.
So as Simon has just explained LLMs can fail at these tasks that are really
central to data analysis. Bluff Bench 1 the first Bluff Bench is evidence that
models can fail to override their priors about data. And then we also saw in the
second eval that they can also fail to notice subtle data quality issues. And
both of these abilities like the ability to not let your expectations interfere
with your ability to see what's right in front of you and the ability to use a
plot or something else to notice data quality issues are really central to data
analysis. These are things that we would want any person doing any kind of data
science to be able to do. And that also applies to agents.
And there's another problem which is that LLMs are really great performers. You
know they can put on this really convincing act of correctness. So we saw
in Bluff Bench the model will readily interpret these plots and it acts very
confident about what it's saying. And it's very easy to sort of fall into this
pattern of trust with them. The only problem is that like in this plot where
we have a clearly positive trend that the model has described as a clear
negative relationship is that it's like this really convincing performance right.
But it's one that occasionally fails to match reality. And these answers all look
the same. They're really hard. It's really hard to distinguish incorrect LLM
responses from correct ones. So here's another plot from Bluff Bench where I
think any person would say you know this looks like a U. It's a parabolic
relationship. And then three responses from the same model. It's a little hard
to read them but like they all have the same tone. They have the same length. The
model is equally confident in all of those. And you would have to look at the
plot to know that the first two are very wrong and the middle one is correct. So
it's not just that the model is making mistakes but that the answers look the
same. It can be very hard to distinguish the correct answers from the wrong ones
unless you already know what the data looks like. OK. So again we see the LLMs
can fail at tasks that are central to data analysis. And not only do they fail
they can cloak these incorrect answers in confident descriptions and it makes
it really hard to tell what's correct and what's not. That sounds a bit
negative. I'm going to say that LLMs are still useful for data analysis and we
don't need to throw this whole endeavor away just because of evidence like Bluff
Bench and Bluff Bench 2. It doesn't mean the LLMs are useless anywhere that
you're doing anything that you value correctness. Instead the task is really
to figure out how they can fit into the work and to design around their
limitations. So I said I'm going to say that LLMs are still useful for data
analysis but we're going to need to do two things in these agents to make them
actually work for us. And the first is to make it as easy as possible for them
to be right. And then the second is that when they inevitably make mistakes to
make it matter less when they're wrong. It's going to prevent mistakes but then
mitigate them when they probably eventually happen. This whole time we've
been talking about agents but just really quickly all I mean when I say
agent is just a model hooked up in a way so that it can gather information from
the world like reading files and then also can alter the world so it can run
code or it can edit your files. And you might already use an agent but you can
also build them yourself and these lessons are probably most relevant if
you're building something yourself or you're altering something that already
exists. At Posit we have an agent called Posit Assistant which is both a general
purpose coding agent for R and Python and also a specialized data analysis
agent. And it lives in our IDEs, Positron and RStudio. And I'm just going to use
this as an example for the rest of the talk. Okay. So I said even though they
make all these mistakes and like they seem, you know, these mistakes we see in
BluffBench are like kind of bad. You know, these are not things that we want a
human agent to do. They're not things we want an LLM agent to do. But LLMs still
have a use for data analysis. They can actually be very useful. But we need to
make it as easy as possible for them to be right. And what this task looks like
is constructing the environment, everything that goes around the model, so
that it's as easy as possible for the model to sort of fall into correctness. We
don't want it to have to work very hard to, you know, be right. We want it to just
fall into this path of correctness. And I'm saying build the environment around
the model. Because typically you control the harness, all of this stuff around the
model, like the prompting and the tools and the skills. And you're not actually
controlling the model itself. Unless, you know, you're one of these labs that makes
both models and the harness. I'm going to talk about two things to construct this
ecosystem around the model that makes it easy to be right. The first is that code
should really be the foundation of what the agent is doing. So, you want to have
the model write code. And then the second is to design the harness with correctness
in mind. Okay. So, when you're making an agent, I think if you want it to be
correct, it is really helpful to lean on code. And there's a couple reasons for
this. The first is that I think by now many people are familiar with this. But
LLMs are actually great at writing code. This is really one of their strengths. And
then the second is that, you know, from years of everyone doing data analysis as
humans, we've learned that code is great for data analysis. It's reproducible,
it's transparent, and it's auditable. And the same things that are true for humans
doing data analysis is true for LLMs doing analysis. We shouldn't, you know,
abandon these learnings of code just because there's a new tool. So, we want
the agent to write code. And then we also want to design the harness with
correctness in mind. So, for Positive Assistant, we have a lot of prompting
that encourages it to prioritize correctness over progress. If you let
models sort of go on their own, they often will just kind of advance the
analysis forward instead of thinking about correctness, subtlety, statistical
rigor. So, we have a lot of prompting encouraging it to follow this path. The
second is having tools that serve the same purposes of correctness. So, these
are things, again, having code is the foundation of what your agent does. Have
the agent run code. You could imagine an agent that, you know, does not run code.
You just hand it a CSV, and it computes, you know, in its head the median of
columns or the number of rows. Generally, it's going to be a lot less successful
than having it run a bit of code, see that result, and then give you the answer.
And then you also want the agent to have enough access to files and environment
and data so that it has a, you know, good chance of building enough context to
actually get the answer right. There's often so much nuance in data analysis,
and a lot of that comes from, you know, not just the data, but all of the context
around that data. And you want the agent to have access to that. Okay. And it
turns out that performance improves when the environment makes it easy to be
right. So, we ran an evaluation on positive assistant on the bluff bench
tasks and compared it to the result from the bluff bench package that just has a
minimal harness in place. All the model can really do there is make a plot. And
it turns out that when you have all this stuff wrapped around the model, pushing
it towards this path of correctness, performance improves. So, generally,
positive assistant has done better on this evaluation than just the minimal
harness present in bluff bench. Okay. So, even with all that said, the agent is
probably still going to make mistakes. You know, humans make mistakes. Models
make mistakes. And so, we need to make it matter less when they're wrong. Okay.
And again, we get a lot of this mitigation from just using code as the
foundation of the agent. One thing code is great for is that it makes auditing
what happened in the analysis easy. And for positive assistant, we didn't just
want the model to write code. Somewhere we wanted the person to be able to see
that code and have a chance to audit it and make catch mistakes. This doesn't
mean that, you know, you need to comb through it every time. But it's there so
you can inspect it if you suspect something has gone wrong and have a
chance at catching a mistake and then diagnosing it. We've also done things
like make it easy to read with syntax highlighting and the formatting just so
this auditing process is more likely to happen. And then positive assistant
also has a shared environment between the user and the agent. So, you can see
eye to eye with the agent. You see the same outputs and run the same code. And
so, the model isn't guessing, you know, what data you have loaded or other
things that are in your environment. It's operating in the same environment
that you as the user are. And this turns out to be very useful, especially for
something like data analysis where it can be very iterative and you're turning
the same object, you know, over and over making small changes. You want to have
a shared environment with the agent. Okay. So, in the first half of this talk,
we said that LLMs can fail at these tasks that are central to data analysis.
But they're still useful for data analysis. Especially if you do a couple
things. One is focus on making it easy for them to be right. You know, as easy
as possible. So, they just fall into this path of correctness. And the second
is to make it matter less when they inevitably do something incorrect.
I have the link to the slides, but also QR code for a newsletter that Simon and I
write every other week. And this week, I think we're going to write about
BluffBench 2, which is that second evaluation about noticing subtle data
quality issues. So, if you want to take a look at it this week, that might be
an interesting follow-up. Thanks.
Thanks. We have lots of questions. So, yeah. So, have you tested your latest
benchmark against GPT 5.6?
Yeah. We did run the BluffBench 2 against GPT 5.6. And it ended up that the model's
results were sort of in the ballpark of GPT 5.5.
Okay.
Is it with maximum thinking?
It's... So, the question was, was that eval run with maximum thinking? So,
when we run this evaluation, we tend to run it with the settings that we would
expect our users to use in Posit Assistant. So, the default thinking setting
in Posit Assistant is medium. And as such, we run the eval against medium because
most users don't change that default.
What about the labels on the plots? If you have the same data with different
labels on the plots, do you get similar results?
For BluffBench 1, we did run it telling the model to ignore the labels. And that
does improve performance because the labels are part of the expectations about
what the plot is going to be. If you're plotting a known data set, and then you
have the X and Y axis labeled in a way that matches the well-known data set, that
feeds into the model's priors. So, we did run the BluffBench 2 against GPT 5.6.
So, I think performance on the first BluffBench would almost certainly improve
if we stripped those, stripped those out. The issue is that, like, you probably
don't want to do this for your agent. We don't want to do this in Posit Assistant
because we want to hand the agent the actual plot object without doing any sort
of manipulation behind the scene, which is probably what you want to, like, you
want the model to be able to look at a reasonable plot without having to do
weird things to manipulate it and be accurate.
Okay. So, what about passing in raw data rather than plots?
Yeah. So, the two BluffBench evaluations are, like, really focused on plots.
In Posit Assistant, I don't know what exactly the question was getting at,
but, like, Posit Assistant or other data analysis agents are going to look at,
you know, if not the actual raw data file to do stuff, like, outputs that make
tables, you know, parts of the data, all of that. I think we're less certain about,
like, the prior conflict issue with tables or with data. Anecdotally, I think we
don't see the issue as much. A lot of the problems have to do with sort of
specifics about what's happening with plots and LLM's ability, like, you know,
visual reasoning abilities generally. But I do think it would be useful and
interesting to do follow-ups where we try to mess with the priors with tables or
parts of the raw data.
Okay. Can you elaborate on what your prompting around correctness looks like?
Are you just saying, telling the agent,
prioritize correctness, or are you giving specific statistical answer?
I just answered two questions.
The question was about the prompting that's available to Posit Assistant.
For the most part, it is sort of along the lines of what the question describes,
like, asking it to prioritize correctness over this performance of progress. So,
rather than making it seem as if the analysis is moving along happily, pausing when there
seem to be data quality issues. If you're interested in reading the prompting of the
agent, you can just ask it. We've told the agent that it's free to share whatever
prompting it has access to. So, it might be an interesting read.
Okay. Can you use Posit Assistant on its own, separate from the Posit ecosystem?
Have you done, like, an ablation analysis to see what instructions help the most?
Would these be reusable in other workflows?
Okay. So, I'll start with the first question. Can you use Posit Assistant on its own,
aside from the Posit ecosystem? One of the interfaces to Posit Assistant, the main two
are in two IDEs we developed, called RStudio and Positron, but there's a third, which is a TUI.
And so, if you wanted to use Posit Assistant without any other Posit things, you could use
the TUI in whatever IDE or in a plain terminal if you wanted.
Okay. So, can Positron's built-in agent access external documentation for auditing correctness?
The question was, can the agent access external documentation for correctness?
So, Posit Assistant is shaped similarly to a cloud code or a codex in terms of the tools
that it has access to. So, it can run bash code, run Python code, run R code. And as such,
it can access the documents that it needs to. Specifically for auditing correctness,
if it's not inside of the directory that you're working in or otherwise mentioned in your
prompting, you would probably need to nudge it in that direction.
Okay. Would you say that inference is like a hypothesis and code execution is like
experimental verification? Can you repeat that?
Oh, yeah. Would you say inference is like a hypothesis and code execution is like
experimental validation? Yeah. I think that sounds about right.
Yeah. If you're treating the code that it runs like nothing is verified until the code has been
run or something, I guess. But even if you're having the agent run code and look at the results,
it's still using so much of what is just in the model itself. It's not just looking at the code
and it's never going to have no priors or no information that it's using to interpret that.
So, there might be some leakage in that metaphor. But that sounds about right.
Okay. What updates to the harness had the biggest gains for accuracy and reliability?
Like, what stood out? We don't know. We're kind of surprised by that.
Okay. Have you ever evaluated confident wrongness of elements against humans?
Humans' confident wrongness. So, I've seen similar egregious levels of wrong confidence
in human beings that ought to know better. So, 100% accuracy may not be the right target.
So, AI versus humans. Yeah.
No, we haven't tried to evaluate confidence compared to human confidence. I feel maybe
unqualified to measure human confidence. At one point, I think we did try to sort of
approximate how confident the model was about its answers and did find that, yeah, like it's not that
it's less confident when it's wrong, which is really sort of a problem. If it was less confident
and was hedged a lot when it was wrong, that would in many ways be a lot better. But it's sort of
equally confident, which, yeah, obviously humans can do as well.
Okay. So, there are a lot more questions. And so, please do look at Slack and maybe answer on Slack
because, you know, this has generated a whole lot of interest, which is great. But we do have to
cut now so that people have time to go between. So, let's everybody thank Sarah and Simon again.